professor Dave here, let's learn about
chemical bonds
a molecule is made up of atoms that are participating in chemical
bonds with one another. there are
different types of bonds that we will
want to be able to describe and the key
to their formation has to do with the
difference in electronegativity between
the two atoms participating in the bond.
if the difference is more than about 2
like with sodium and chlorine, chlorine
will steal an electron from sodium
chlorine really wants another electron,
sodium really wants to get rid of one so
everybody wins. the result is a
positively charged sodium ion and a
negatively charged chloride ion.
particles of opposite charge have an
electrostatic attraction so these two
ions hang out together by forming an
ionic bond. this is a very strong
attraction because it is happening
between ions that have a formal charge.
bond, ionic bond. electrons taken not
shared. speaking of shared electrons if
the difference in electronegativity
between the two atoms is less than about
1.7 no electrons are stolen but instead
the two atoms share two electrons. the
electron from this atom feels the
attraction from the other nucleus and so
does the electron from this atom, so the
atoms share the two electrons to form a
covalent bond. covalent bonds can be
polar or nonpolar. if the
electronegativity difference between the
atoms is not high enough to cause
ionization but is at least more than
0.5, like with hydrogen and chlorine,
instead of completely stealing the
electron the chlorine will just sort of
hog the electrons in the resulting
covalent bond. the more electronegative
atom in a polar covalent bond pulls the
electron density towards itself and as a
result of the slight electron excess we
call this atom partially negative,
denoted by the symbol Delta minus. the
atom whose electron is getting pulled
away is slightly electron deficient and
therefore partially positive or Delta
plus. if the electronegativity difference
is less than 0.5 the covalent bond is said to be
non polar. in a nonpolar covalent bond the
electrons are shared more or less evenly
or in the case of two atoms of the same
element, precisely evenly. the atoms will
have no partial charges at all. other
than strange phenomena like metallic
bonding these are the main ways atoms
bind to one another
remember that you can predict the type
of bond that will form between two
elements by comparing their
electronegativites. if the difference
is very low, less than 0.5 or so, it will be
a nonpolar covalent bond where the
electrons are shared evenly. between
about 0.5 and 1.7 it'll be a polar
covalent bond with the electrons are
shared but one atom holds them more
tightly. if above 2 or so one atom
will simply steal an electron from the
other and you'll get ions that are
joined by on ionic bond. thanks for
watching guys, subscribe to my channel
for more tutorials and as always feel
free to email me